Eloise Hubbard Linscott collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Eloise Hubbard Linscott collection 1815-2002 1932-1955
AFC 1942/002
Linscott, Eloise Hubbard
34 boxes (18 linear feet); 198 folders.
11 sound cylinders: analog.
441 sound discs: analog; various sizes.
32 sound tape reels: analog; various sizes.
1 sound cassette: analog.
circa 200 photographs: photographic prints, negatives; various sizes.
12 drawings.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Eloise Hubbard Linscott’s collection of research materials for her book, Folk Songs of Old New England (1939) and other folk music research through about 1955. The collection includes correspondence; music transcriptions; sound recordings of folk music, lectures, and radio broadcasts; photographs of Linscott's informants; documentation of events and trips within New England; plus some materials from her estate, dated circa 1815-2002.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Barry, Phillips, 1880-1937--Correspondence.; Bartholomew, Marshall, 1885-1978--Correspondence.; Bayard, Samuel Preston--Correspondence.; Bayard, Samuel Preston.; Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948--Correspondence.; Carpenter, James Madison, 1888-1983--Correspondence.; Coolidge, Harold J. (Harold Jefferson), 1904-1985--Correspondence.; Farnham, H. Rae. Passing thoughts.; Flanders, Helen Hartness, 1890-1972--Correspondence.; Grover, Carrie B., 1879-1959; Grover, Carrie B., 1979-1959--Correspondence.; Knott, Sarah Gertrude, 1895-1984--Correspondence.; Lenski, Lois, 1893-1974--Correspondence.; Linscott, Eloise Hubbard, 1897-1978; Linscott, Eloise Hubbard, 1897-1978--Correspondence.; Linscott, Eloise Hubbard, 1897-1978--Ethnomusicological collections.; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002--Correspondence.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982--Correspondence.; Reed, Elizabeth Foster.; Sherrard, William J., 1877-1975; Sherrard, William J., 1877-1975--Correspondence.; Speck, Frank G. (Frank Gouldsmith), 1881-1950--Correspondence.; Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1882-1944--Correspondence.; Walden, Arthur Treadwell, 1871-1947. Songs of the Yukon trail.
Organizations
Archive of American Folk Song; Federal Writers' Project of the Works Progress Administration for the State of New Hampshire--Correspondence.; Macmillan & Co.--Correspondence.; National Folk Festival Association--Correspondence.
Subjects
American poetry--20th century.; Ballads, English--New England.; Children's songs, English--New England.; Cochiti Indians--Music.; Fiddle tunes--New England.; Fiddling--New England.; Field recordings--Massachusetts.; Field recordings--New England.; Field recordings--New Hampshire.; Folk dance music--New England.; Folk festivals--New England.; Folk music--New England.; Folk songs, English--New England.; Folk songs, French--New England.; French-Canadians--New England--Music.; Games--New England.; Hymns, English--New England.; Indians of North America--New England--Music.; Irish Americans--New England--Music.; Loggers--New England--Songs and music.; Lullabies--New England.; Navajo Indians--Music.; Passamaquoddy Indians--Music.; Popular music--New England--19th century--Manuscripts.; Popular music--United States--1931-1940.; Popular music--United States--1941-1950.; Sea songs--New England.; Shakers--Hymns.; Singing games--New England.; Square dancing--New England.; Wampanoag Indians--Music.; Yodels--New England.
Places
United States--History--War of 1812--Songs and music.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Drawings.; Field notes.; Field recordings.; Lecture notes.; Lectures.; Photographs.; Radio programs.; Sound recordings.
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts, II. Sound Recordings, III. Graphic Materials, IV. Electronic Media.
Acquisition
The 1942 accrual included all materials pertaining to Linscott's 1941 fieldwork, and the 1983 accrual was a bequest from her estate.
Accruals
Collection materials arrived in two accruals: the first in 1942, and the second in 1983.
Separated Material
Documents and recordings belonging and unrelated to Linscott's collecting activities were returned to the family.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Additional Formats
Significant selections from this collection have been digitized and are available in the Folklife Reading Room.
Biographical Notes
Eloise Hubbard Linscott (1897-1978) was born Eloise Barrett Hubbard, and raised in Taunton, Massachusetts, with her two sisters and three brothers. She studied at Radcliffe College from 1916-1920, and earned an A.B. in English literature. Among other classes, she took The History of Choral Music, with Archibald T. Davison, also the conductor of the Harvard Glee Club, and who in addition to his own noted scholarship (on various aspects of music), was the mentor of composer Randall Thompson. While Linscott made at least one attempt to further her education, her studies at Radcliffe were the extent of her higher education. After she married Charles Hardy Linscott (in 1921), they lived in Needham, Massachusetts, and spent summers in Wolfeboro, New Hampshire. New England was Eloise Hubbard Linscott’s home for her entire life. The Linscotts had one son, John Hubbard Linscott, born in 1929.
In interviews, Linscott offered two recollections of how she began her fieldwork. One story was that the songs she collected, when published, would fill a void where no music book on traditional songs, such as those she knew as a girl, existed to date. The other story was that she simply wanted to preserve the legacy of a musical tradition within her own family. Friends took an interest in her work and wished to participate, and the project grew from that point. At some stage her work seemed to take on a life of its own. The culmination of ten years’ work (by her own estimate) was Folk Songs of Old New England (Macmillan, 1939). Although she continued her research and fieldwork, with the intention of publishing other books, Folk Songs of Old New England was her sole known publication. However, she was a frequent speaker at various clubs and venues, and was also interviewed for at least one known radio broadcast (in 1955; see SR418 in this collection). Due to ill health, Linscott sometimes had to limit her travels, but she maintained her interest in folksongs until her death.
Linscott used her own household funds to finance the first ten years of her research. Around 1940, she gained sponsorship from Musicraft and in 1941 from the Library of Congress, whose Archive of Folk Song (now incorporated into the American Folklife Center) loaned to Linscott a recording machine and blank discs. The Library’s proviso was that the master recordings would be given to the Library of Congress. Copies of Linscott’s fieldwork from November and December 1941 (both recordings and typed fieldnotes), were accessioned by the Library in 1942. Linscott benefited from the advice of Alan Lomax, who was a regular correspondent with her during this time, in his role as the assistant-in-charge of the Archive of Folk Song. Linscott’s enterprising and tenacious style, as well as her energy and enthusiasm, earned her the nickname “the Tornado” from Herbert D. (Bert) Farnham (one of her informants). Her fieldnotes reflect a real fondness for those people whose work she recorded, and who opened their homes and shared their stories.
Over the course of her life as a collector, she gathered approximately 2500 recordings (according to her own estimate), on cylinders, discs, and tapes. Much of the fieldwork, gathered before, during, and after World War II, reflects the urgent feeling that these traditions must be gathered and preserved for future generations.
Scope and Content
This collection of sound recordings, photographs, and manuscripts (including correspondence and other research materials) was compiled by Eloise Hubbard Linscott and represents her research for her book, Folksongs of Old New England (1939), and her unpublished manuscripts and folk music research through about 1955. Among Linscott's many correspondents were Phillips Barry, Ruth Benedict, Marshall Bartholomew, Samuel P. Bayard, James M. Carpenter, Harold J. Coolidge, Jr., Helen Hartness Flanders, Carrie B. Grover, Sarah Gertrude Knott, Lois Lenski, National Folk Festival, Frank G. Speck, Hendrik Willem van Loon, various correspondents at the Library of Congress including Archibald MacLeish, Alan Lomax, Benjamin A. Botkin, Harold Spivacke, and others; and various publishers, recording companies, radio stations, and administrators of summer camps. Twenty-five glass-based lacquer discs of Lincott's field recordings with field notes were accessioned by the Library of Congress Archive of American Folk Song in 1942. The recordings include folk music, folk songs, children's songs, sea songs, lumberjack songs, fiddle tunes, and dance music, including dance calls. Other sound recordings in the collection are radio broadcasts, lectures delivered by Linscott, recordings of Linscott's family, and a few American Indian and French Canadian songs. The collection includes music transcriptions of fiddle tunes, some made by Samuel Preston Bayard, circa 1944; and Linscott's transcriptions of music and lyrics. Photographs include pictures of Linscott's informants, her documentation of events and trips, and photographs of New England landscapes. A manuscript of poetry by Arthur Treadwell Walden titled "Songs of the Yukon Trail," and a small book of poetry, "Passing Thoughts," by H. Rae Farnham are included; both were informants of Linscott. Included with Linscott's estate, received at the Library in 1983, is a manuscript music notebook, undated, but circa 1815, belonging to Samuel Reed, and to Linscott's great grandmother, Elizabeth Foster Reed, containing popular songs and dance music, marches, and music from the War of 1812. The collection also includes administrative correspondence related to the digitization of selected collection materials in 2002.
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Subseries A: Administrative files
    - Finding aid, 51 pages (approximate) (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Collection inventory (early version) 1988, 5 pages (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Content list of Linscott cylinders, from the Federal Cylinder Project, circa 1984, 2 pages (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Administrative correspondence, circa 1940-1985, 90 pages (approximate) (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Song titles provided (or amended) by Dudley Laufman, 2002-2003, 13 pages (Box-folder 1/5)
      At the request of Marcia K. Segal, Dudley Laufman, fiddler and fiddle music expert from New Hampshire, listened to digitized recordings from the collection, in order to identify untitled tunes. In addition, he offered alternate titles and amended other titles
    - Song titles provided (or amended) by Nicholas Hawes, 2003, 12 pages (Box-folder 1/6)
      At the request of Marcia K. Segal, Nicholas Hawes, fiddler and fiddle music expert, listened to digitized recordings from the collection, in order to identify untitled tunes. In addition, he offered alternate titles and amended other titles, and provided songwriting credits and dates for several works.
    - SIG (Systems Integration Group, Inc.) (contractor), 2001-2002, 65 pages (approximate) (Box-folder 1/7)
      SIG digitized the collection's manuscript materials.
    - Cutting Corporation (contractor), 2002, 15 pages (Box-folder 1/8)
      Cutting Corp.digitized the collection's audio materials and disc sleeves.
    - JJT (contractor), 2001, 65 pages (approximate) (Box-folder 1/9)
      JJT digitized the collection's photographic materials.
  - Subseries B: Correspondence
    - Sub-subseries: General correspondence with Linscott
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1932-1936, 36 pages; afc1942002_ms001 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1937, 65 pages; afc1942002_ms002 (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1938, 63 pages; afc1942002_ms003 (Box-folder 1/12)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1939, 51 pages; afc1942002_ms004 (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 1 of 2), 1940, 66 pages; afc1942002_ms005 (Box-folder 2/14)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 2 of 2), 1940, 61 pages; afc1942002_ms006 (Box-folder 2/15)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1941, 58 pages; afc1942002_ms007 (Box-folder 2/16)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1942, 22 pages; afc1942002_ms008 (Box-folder 2/17)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1943, 43 pages; afc1942002_ms009 (Box-folder 2/18)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 1 of 2), 1944, 78 pages; afc1942002_ms010 (Box-folder 2/19)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 2 of 2), 1944, 53 pages; afc1942002_ms011 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1945, 53 pages; afc1942002_ms012 (Box-folder 2/21)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1946, 39 pages; afc1942002_ms013 (Box-folder 3/22)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1947, 20 pages; afc1942002_ms014 (Box-folder 3/23)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1948, 29 pages; afc1942002_ms015 (Box-folder 3/24)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1949, 10 pages; afc1942002_ms016 (Box-folder 3/25)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1950-1951, 22 pages; afc1942002_ms017 (Box-folder 3/26)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1952-1954, 27 pages; afc1942002_ms018 (Box-folder 3/27)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1955, 37 pages; afc1942002_ms019 (Box-folder 3/28)
        Includes correspondence with Clare Cassidy, who interviewed Linscott for the WTAG radio program, “Folk Festival,” recorded on January 12, 1955, and broadcast four days later, on January 16.
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1956-1959, 24 pages; afc1942002_ms020 (Box-folder 3/29)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1960-1964, 28 pages; afc1942002_ms021 (Box-folder 3/30)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1965, 12 pages; afc1942002_ms022 (Box-folder 3/31)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1966-1967, 34 pages; afc1942002_ms023 (Box-folder 3/32)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1973-1978, 30 pages; afc1942002_ms024 (Box-folder 4/33)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1932-1939, 24 pages; afc1942002_ms025 (Box-folder 4/34)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 1 of 4), 1940-1941, 33 pages; afc1942002_ms026 (Box-folder 4/35)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 2 of 4), 1940-1941, 39 pages; afc1942002_ms027 (Box-folder 4/36)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 3 of 4), 1940-1941, 28 pages; afc1942002_ms028 (Box-folder 4/37)
        Folders 37 and 38 were digitized with one ID number, and divided into separate folders after digitization.
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 4 of 4), 1940-1941, 44 pages; afc1942002_ms028 (Box-folder 4/38)
        See description for Folder 37.
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 1 of 2), 1942-1950, 24 pages; afc1942002_ms029 (Box-folder 4/39)
      - Correspondence to Linscott (Folder 2 of 2), 1942-1950, 38 pages; afc1942002_ms030 (Box-folder 4/40)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1951-1959, 34 pages; afc1942002_ms031 (Box-folder 4/41)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1960-1966, 37 pages; afc1942002_ms032 (Box-folder 5/42)
      - Correspondence to Linscott, 1972-1977, 10 pages; afc1942002_ms033 (Box-folder 5/43)
    - Sub-subseries: Business correspondence
      - Correspondence to Macmillan Company, 1932-1943, 66 pages; afc1942002_ms034 (Box-folder 5/44)
        Macmillan Company was the original publisher for Folk Songs of Old New England
      - Correspondence to Macmillan Company, 1944-1955, 22 pages; afc1942002_ms035 (Box-folder 4/45)
      - Correspondence from Macmillan Company, 1932-1936, 8 pages; afc1942002_ms036 (Box-folder 5/46)
      - Correspondence from Macmillan Company, 1937, 22 pages; afc1942002_ms037 (Box-folder 5/47)
      - Correspondence from Macmillan Company, 1938, 23 pages; afc1942002_ms038 (Box-folder 5/48)
      - Correspondence from Macmillan Company, 1939, 37 pages; afc1942002_ms039 (Box-folder 5/49)
      - Correspondence from Macmillan Company, 1940, 20 pages; afc1942002_ms040 (Box-folder 5/50)
      - Correspondence from Macmillan Company (Folder 1 of 2), 1941-1957, 31 pages; afc1942002_ms041 (Box-folder 6/51)
      - Correspondence from Macmillan Company (Folder 2 of 2), 1941-1957, 21 pages; afc1942002_ms042 (Box-folder 6/52)
      - Correspondence with Bruce Humphries, Inc., 1944-1946, 53 pages; afc1942002_ms044 (Box-folder 6/53)
      - Correspondence with ASCAP, 1957, 5 pages; afc1942002_ms043 (Box-folder 6/54)
    - Sub-subseries: Fall Folk Festival correspondence
      - Correspondence relating to the Fall Folk Festival (Folder 1 of 2), 1944, 30 pages; afc1942002_ms044 (Box-folder 6/55)
        Folders 55 and 56 were digitized with one ID number, and divided into separate folders after digitization.
      - Correspondence relating to the Fall Folk Festival (Folder 2 of 2), 1944, 89 pages; afc1942002_ms045 (Box-folder 6/56)
        See description for Folder 55.
    - Sub-subseries: Correspondence with specific individuals
      - Correspondence from Carrie B. Grover (Folder 1 of 2), 1942-1954, 96 pages; afc1942002_ms046 (Box-folder 6/57)
        Folders 57 and 58 were digitized with one ID number, and divided into separate folders after digitization.
      - Correspondence from Carrie B. Grover (Folder 2 of 2), 1942-1954, 82 pages; afc1942002_ms046 (Box-folder 6/58)
        See description for Folder 57.
      - Correspondence with William J. (Jack) Sherrard (Folder 1 of 2), circa 1944-1969, 73 pages; afc1942002_ms047 (Box-folder 7/59)
      - Correspondence with William J. (Jack) Sherrard (Folder 2 of 2), circa 1944-1969, 66 pages; afc1942002_ms048 (Box-folder 7/60)
      - Correspondence from William J. (Jack) Sherrard, circa 1960-1969, 84 pages; afc1942002_ms049 (Box-folder 7/61)
    - Sub-subseries: Miscellaneous correspondence
      - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Folder 1 of 3), circa 1920-1955, 41 pages; afc1942002_ms097 (Box-folder 8/62)
      - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Folder 2 of 3), circa 1920-1955, 35 pages; afc1942002_ms050 (Box-folder 8/63)
        Folders 63 and 64 were digitized with one ID number, and divided into separate folders after digitization.
      - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Folder 3 of 3), circa 1920-1955, 41 pages; afc1942002_ms050 (Box-folder 8/64)
        See description for Folder 63.
      - Envelopes and envelope fragments (original), circa 1943-1969, 12 items (Box-folder 8/65)
      - Envelopes (photocopies), circa 1960-1969, 11 pages (Box-folder 8/66)
      - Correspondence and materials related to the Peaked Hill Boys (photocopies), 1936-1944, 17 pages (Box-folder 8/67)
        Materials loaned to Linscott by Elna Sherman. Willie Woodard, who was recorded by Linscott, was the leader of the Peaked Hill Boys.
      - Business correspondence (various), circa 1945-1960, 13 pages (Box-folder 8/68)
      - Form letter from Jackson Martindell, circa 1961, 2 pages (Box-folder 8/69)
        This item originally accompanied letter from Marquis-Who’s Who, Inc. (see Folder 30).
      - Correspondence and mailing lists related to republication of Folk Songs of Old New England, circa 1962, 22 pages (Box-folder 8/70)
        Includes correspondence, a mailing list, a draft mailing list with notes, and a note accompanying a complimentary copy of Folk Songs of New England (second edition).
  - Subseries C: Fieldnotes, lyrics, and music transcriptions
    - Fieldnotes, transcriptions, etc., 1940-1941, 131 pages; afc1942002_ms053 (Box-folder 8/71)
    - Unbound notes from folder entitled “Fieldnotes, Transcriptions, Etc.”, undated, 10 pages; afc1942002_ms093 (Box-folder 8/72)
    - Report of field trip: November 4-17, and December 2-3, 1941 (draft), 1941, 21 pages (Box-folder 8/73)
    - Report of field trip: November 4-17, and December 2-3, 1941, 1941, 24 pages; afc1942002_ms057 (Box-folder 8/74)
    - Unbound materials from folder entitled “Notes for Field Trip: November 4-17, December 2-3, 1941”, 1941, 3 pages; afc1942002_ms095 (Box-folder 8/75)
    - Expenses and discography for field trip of November 4-17, December 2-3, 1941, 1941, 10 pages (Box-folder 8/76)
    - Fieldnotes, lecture notes, etc., circa 1943-1944, 96 pages; afc1942002_ms055 (Box-folder 8/77)
    - Unbound notes from folder entitled “Fieldnotes, Lecture notes, etc., 1943-circa 1950s, 10 pages; afc1942002_ms094 (Box-folder 8/78)
      The notes date from circa 1950s.
    - Fieldnotes, dance instructions, transcriptions, etc., circa 1944-1946, 51 pages; afc1942002_ms052 (Box-folder 8/79)
    - Fieldnotes, dance instructions, research notes, etc., undated, 71 pages; afc1942002_ms056 (Box-folder 9/80)
    - Song log (selected recordings), fieldnotes, transcriptions, etc., circa 1942, 96 pages; afc1942002_ms051 (Box-folder 9/81)
    - Unbound notes from folder entitled “Song Log (Selected Recordings), fieldnotes, transcriptions, etc.,” undated, 3 pages; afc1942002_ms092 (Box-folder 9/82)
    - Song titles, notes, etc., circa 1951, 24 pages; afc1942002_ms054 (Box-folder 9/83)
    - Transcriptions, bookkeeping, fieldnotes, instructions for use of disc-cutting equipment, etc., circa 1940-1941, 81 pages; afc1942002_ms060 (Box-folder 9/84)
    - Square dances (list of locations), plus fieldnotes from a trip to a reservation, undated, 12 pages; afc1942002_ms058 (Box-folder 9/85)
      See note for Folder 86.
    - Field trip to a reservation, circa 1940s, 2 pages; afc1942002_ms059 (Box-folder 9/86)
      While it is not specifically named in the documentation, this was probably Indian Township, Maine, specifically Peter Dana Point, and possibly Indian Township as well.
    - Ballads sent to Eloise Hubbard Linscott by Hazel Andrews, undated, 27 pages; afc1942002_ms073 (Box-folder 9/87)
    - Cover sheet for the copy book of Elizabeth Foster Reed (Folder 1 of 2), 1 page; afc1942002_ms071 (Box-folder 9/88)
      Contains the modern cover sheet (undated) that accompanies the copy book (also known as a music manuscript notebook). See Folder 89 for a description of the copy book. Folders 88 and 89 were digitized with one ID number, and divided into separate folders after digitization.
    - Copy book of Elizabeth Foster Reed (Folder 2 of 2), 41 pages; afc1942002_ms071 (Box-folder 9/89)
      Contains the bound volume, a music manuscript once owned by Elizabeth Foster Reed and Samuel Reed. See Folder 88 for the modern cover sheet that accompanies this item. See description for Folder 63.
    - Fiddle tunes, transcribed by Samuel Preston Bayard, circa 1944, 59 pages; afc1942002_ms063 (Box-folder 9/90)
      See correspondence from Bayard to Linscott (1944 and 1945) regarding his transcription work
    - Sea chanteys (transcribed by Linscott), sung by William J. (Jack) Sherrard, undated, 26 pages; afc1942002_ms061 (Box-folder 9/91)
    - Scales and exercises, plus folk tunes, circa 1938, 20 pages; afc1942002_ms068 (Box-folder 9/92)
    - Transcribed music, undated, 22 pages; afc1942002_ms067 (Box-folder 9/93)
      Transcriptions may be the work both of Linscott and of Samuel Preston Bayard.
    - Transcribed music and lyrics, circa 1943, 48 pages; afc1942002_ms062 (Box-folder 9/94)
      Includes notes by Linscott, transcriptions by Samuel Preston Bayard, and an unidentified person.
    - Transcribed music and lyrics, undated, 24 pages; afc1942002_ms064 (Box-folder 9/95)
    - Transcribed music and lyrics, plus notes, circa 1938, 21 pages; afc1942002_ms065 (Box-folder 9/96)